Register of the Robert Dark papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Dark Papers,
1917-1964
77078
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 5 card file boxes, 6 envelopes, 2 oversize boxes (6.7 linear feet)
Orders, correspondence, speeches, clippings, and photographs relating to the U.S. Army in the Philippines, 1931-1932, the activities of the 321st Infantry Regiment in the Pacific Theater, 1942-1946, and the invasion of Angaur and Peleliu Island, 1944. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Dark, Robert, 1894-1976.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1894 September Born, North Carolina
1912 Joined United States Army as a private of the Cavalry branch
1915 Noncommissioned Officer, Coast Artillery Corps
1917 Second Lieutenant, Infantry branch
1917-1919 Served with American Expeditionary Force in France, attained rank of brevet Major
1931-1932 Served at Zamboanga, Mindanao, Philippine Islands
1932-1933 Served at Vancouver Barracks, Washington
1941 Colonel, United States Army
1942-1946 Regimental commander, 321st Infantry Regiment, 81st Division, (1942-1944, trained in continental United States; 1944-1945, fought in Pacific campaigns, 1945-1946, served with occupation troops on Kyushu, Japan).
1946 Resigned from United States Army.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 321st.; Philippines--Defenses.; Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Correspondence, 1935-1946
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Collier, W. A., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Dark, Robert, 1944
  - McDowell, C. R., 1944
  - Meachum, L. T., 1935
  - O'Hanlon, Redmond, 1945
- Subject file, 1931-1964
  Memoranda, orders, printed matter, charts, notes, etc., arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Camp Horn, Arizona, manouver grid, 1943 (Box 1-2)
  - Civilian Conservation Corps, Medford, Oregon, 1933
  - Commendations, 1942-1946
  - Eighty-First Division
    - Divisional newspaper, Wildcat, 1945
    - Memoranda and manouver notes, 1943
    - Newspapers, San Luis Obispo Independent, and San Francisco Examiner, 1944
    - Officer list, 1944
    - Operation report, "Ulithi Atoll, and other Western Carolines-Islands, 21 September 1944-4 January 1945."
    - Operation report, "Operations on Peleliu Island, 23 September 1944-27 November 1944."
    - Operation report, "Palau Island to New Caledonia, to Leyte Islands, to Japan, 5 January 1945-10 January 1946."
    - Poetry
    - Special orders, 1942-1943
  - Operation Stalemate II, draft of United States Marine Corps official history of Palau phase, western Carolines operation, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Petit Barracks, Zamboanga, Mindanao, Philippine Islands, 1931
  - Petit Barracks, Zamboanga, post regulations, 1931
  - Three Hundred Twenty-First Infantry Regiment
    - Air ground tests, Camp San Luis Obispo, 1944
    - Company "L", Christmas program, 1942
    - Manouver adjutant's manouver file, 1944
    - Manouver handbook, undated
    - Movement, Camp Horn to Camp San Luis Obispo, 1943
    - Officer list, undated
    - Organization day, 1942
  - Vancouver Barracks, Washington, 1932
- Speeches and writings, undated
  Writing and speech as listed.
  - "Notes on National Defense," typewritten carbon copy (Box 2)
  - Speech relating to Moro tribe on Mindanao, typewritten, undated
- Miscellany
  Pamphlets, reports, greeting cards, drawings, and photographic negatives.
  - Miscellaneous clippings, greeting cards, printed reports, 1918-1944 (Box 2)
  - Photographic negative file, scenes of Camp Rucker, Horn, San Luis Obispo, Beale, and Pacific campaigns (Box 3-5)
  - Scrapbooks, assembled by Robert Dark, including newspaper clippings magazine articles, and photographs relating to his career and the units with which he served, 1933-1944 (Box 6-7)
- Audio-Visual File
  See photo card catalog.
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1943-1945
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1943-1945